hi everyone uh welcome to magnet seminar uh from
the magnets team uh today I'm really happy to uh
to have James Bryson to uh to this seminar
I would like just to remind everybody that
the format is typically 25 minutes because
in fashion followed by a q a time and there
is a time where Dan is not recorded for
a catch up that you're welcome to stay
um so today we have James Bryson from University
of Oxford in the UK presenting uh the talk
entitled elucidating early solar system Evolution
using the magnetism of carbonacious chondrites
uh Thanks James please um go ahead and share
your screen the floor is yours thank you
brilliant thank you can everyone see my screen
yes that's fine thank you very much excellent
so thank you for that introduction and thank you
for inviting me to speak today I'm really excited
about about giving this talk so during just
the first 45 million years supporting ignition
of our son our soul system underwent a profound
transformation from this chaotic protein planetary
disc of dust and gas I'm sure an example of here
on the left into an organized system of planetary
bodies and the behavior of each planet in our
solar system including their ability to do or
to not support life can trace its Origins back
to the processes involved in this transformation
so the phenomena and the behaviors operated
in our project proprietary disk set the scene
for each planet's pre-evolutionary pathway and
the reason the Earth books where it does today
is because the process of all its formation and
that's true with every planet in our solar system
or indeed any extra battery system as well
now there are several phenomena that govern
how the disk behaves and one of them is this
vast magnetic field that threaded the disk
this material is made up of dust and gas and
that can become ionized by solar radiation and
cosmic rays and that material is moving around
so similar to the Dynamo today he creates a vast
magnetic field now unlike the geodynamo actually
measuring this magnetic field directly today is
really difficult a because our protection tested
our solar system came from dissipated four or five
million years after the Sun ignited so four
and a half billion years ago and while we do
have these telescope images of other disks it's
really difficult to isolate uh the contributions
that we're seeing from their magnetic fields but
there are some sort of very basic fundamental
bits of physics about how proteop discs behave
and by looking at certain Force balances we can
predict broadly what the magnetic field must have
looked like um based on the sort of the the key
principles about how these objects behave and I'm
I'm going to caveat this by saying there's several
models and and they do vary but they all have sort
of certain commonalities and what I'm showing here
is the prediction of of one of these models so to
start with they all vary by orders of magnitude
as a function of distance away from the Sun so uh
zero astronomical units is the sun one astronaut
One AU astronomical unit by definition is where
Earth is and then Neptune is out at 30. uh so
we're seeing this variation by orders of magnitude
uh between Earth and where Jupiter is today at 5
Au we broadly have Planet free strengths magnetic
fields inside the disk itself between 10 and 100
microtesla and then we uh all the models also show
that we have large or strong magnetic fields close
to the Sun and weak magnetic fields far away from
the Sun and this is simply a result of the fact
that we have high densities of dust and gas near
the star far away as we see this exponential decay
in the density dust and gas we have an exponential
decay in the intensity of the magnetic field
as well now this prediction predates these
groundbreaking observations that we've been
measuring over the last seven years or so using
the alma telescope and what these are showing
is that these discs were not smoothly varying
objects they've got these these rings in them and
this prediction the magnetic field intensity you
just kind of cannot include these Rings because
they're just not part of the model in reality what
we might expect is a magnetic field profile that
looks more something like this now this is just
a hypothetical example I created for this to talk
but you can see it's got these variations in um
magnetic field Maxima and Minima that reflect here
we have pressure Maxima and Minima now the really
exciting thing about this is that spinning out of
these Alma telescope observations are this Suite
of new models a planet formation that have really
started to get over the problems that we've been
having for the last 30 years in Planet building
and they basically seemingly solved it if
there are places in our protein Pantry disk
where we had above canonical pressures of dust
and gas and we do see these in these disks but
probing these pressure the Maxima is really
difficult when we look uh at meteorites a
date from this time in our solar system but one
way we could do it is by looking at magnetism
because that pressure Maxima corresponds
to a peak in the magnetic field as well
so these non-uniformities can serve as catalysts
for the entire process of Planet building
but accessing that is difficult but we had
a thorough record with a magnetic field and
its Behavior throughout operator battery disk
we would gain really powerful unique insights
into these features the nature and what created
them so we could really make some big leaps
in saying how potentially we build planets
and potentially deciphering Earth's origin
now I'm not going to go into the details right
now but we believe that we can gain access to
this magnetic field record by studying
particularly ancient meteorites those
that recorded the magnetic field within the first
four to five million years of solar system history
those meteorites are expected to record uh disk
magnetic fields whereas ones later could be
recording called Dynamo fields or other sources
of magnetic field and what I'm showing here is
a compilation of measurements that we've been
doing on meteorites in the last seven years or
so uh that I'm showing their pale intensity is a
function of of time after solar system formation
that's what this term here means um uh and
what I before I get going into what this figure
actually shows for those people who don't work on
meteorites every day when we have these different
groups of chondrites like Co CMS CR CV this
meteorite here is also a CV each group we think uh
represent fragments from the same parent asteroid
so there are about 600 Co chondrites and then we
think they are 600 fragments of the same parent
asteroid so we might expect things that have got
similar namings on here to show similar magnetic
field records and that's seemingly not the case in
fact when we look at this trend at face value
we're seeing really large variations in paleo
density over two waters of magnitude and also over
a short time periods in terms of interpreting this
record the two measurements on here that are most
straightforward to interpret based on the type of
remnants and the measurements we have are these
two uh and that suggests a really precipitous
drop in the magnetic field intensity of a really
short amount of time so if we wanted to look at
these data to try and say did we have a magnetic
field maximum I just did we have a pressure Maxima
and was that where planets were forming right now
this is not overly conclusive but I want to try
and shed some light on that and I'm going to do
that today by talking about this group here the
the CM contract so I'm going to talk about a
particularly uh exciting a special cm condrate
which is the winch you can see game contrite
now there are a number of reasons why this is
a really exciting meteorite uh principally because
it's the freshest meteorite we have in our Global
collection it was picked up within 12 hours of
falling now in terms of its magnetism that's
not super critical but in terms of its organic
um uh molecule concentration uh and it's water
concentration those are very quickly contaminated
on Earth so from a rural planetary science point
of view this meteorite has been a game changer
uh it's also sort of exciting because it's the
first meteorite to have fallen in the UK in the
last 30 years and it's one of these CM contracts
which again we only have about 600 odds so it's
a rare type of meteor we have 70 000 meteorites
in total um we have a camera Network in the UK
that is constantly observing the night sky to
look for meteorites when they enter our atmosphere
and on the 28th of February 2021 they all lit up
with this Fireball streaking across whales uh and
through these these high resolution uh Advanced
cameras overnight we were able to come up with a
prediction of where we think the meteorite should
have landed and really coincidentally it was just
north of Oxford so we put out a press release uh
in the morning news saying if about 10 p.m last
night you saw or heard anything that was a little
bit weird like something crashing around your
house please let us know also if possible please
put on rubber gloves if you have gloves and put
it in plastic bags and then put it in the fridge
um and a family in gloucestershire north
of here you heard what they described as
someone breaking a pane of glass outside their
house at about 10 pm so they woke up heard the
local news and thought they'd check it out and
they found this on their driveway uh which is
as it turns out a piece of this meteorite they
followed exactly what we said which was brilliant
and that night we were at their house to confirm
that this was indeed a piece of this meteorite now
that we knew that we had some of it safely made it
to the ground we sprung into action and went and
searched in the March whether in the Cotswolds to
look for more of this meteorite um and as sort of
a uk-wide planet lab-based planetary science
Community uh we all sort of pitched together
here and we put up a Consortium we constructed a
Consortium to study this meteorite in all of its
details and the Magnetic measurements are being
laid out of Oxford but it's composed or being run
at least entirely by early career scientists it's
been this really amazing opportunity to be part of
within seven days of the meteorite falling we had
over half a kilogram of material a good portion
of that coming from the driveway and another
good portion coming from a big stone that was
found in a field which I showed a picture of on
on the title side and to the present day we've
collected just over 600 grams and this ranges
from millimeter size objects to centimeter size
objects as well as a whole bunch of powder to make
sure we've got as much material as we physically
could we actually even cut up the Wilcox family
driveway and the whole driveway is in the Natural
History Museum uh just make sure we can pluck
out every bit of powder that's embedded in it
we we did also replace the driveway and this is
what it looks like in the sem here I'm showing
a chemical map of iron calcium magnesium in
green blue red uh and what we can see is this
is a very typical for a CM Contour right what this
meteorite was when it accreted to form its parent
asteroid was Olivine pyroxine various glasses
stoichiometric iron sulfide iron nickel metal and
a whole bunch of ice and as that material created
into apparent asteroid that started producing
heat the ice melted reacted with those anhydrous
phases to create a range of hydrate or secondary
aqueously altered minerals and that's what
we're seeing in this meteorite now it's composed
predominantly now of Finance silicates uh to chill
tonight which is a rare uh uh hydroxy sulfide that
you really only find in this type of meteorite uh
carbonates predominantly calcite Remnant olivino
pyroxine and in the red grains and then from a
magnetic point of view it's got magnetite and
it's got non-stoichiometric fine sulfide now so
Superior type and within a month we had two pieces
here in Oxford uh to do magnetic characters each
and measurements on uh so we measured histories
for Soups and we measured Fork diagrams um
I should say that the first paper describing
everything to do with meteorite should hopefully
be out in the next month or so in science advances
um and what we can see from the fork diagrams
these meteorites in particular this one on the
piece of this meteorite sorry particularly
on the left is quite a triangular shape uh
it's less apparent this one although it's
you can just about see the weak signal
down here now sort of going Beyond just that
qualitative description of a forward diagram
we put these into the new principle component
analysis which has been developed in Cambridge
Imperial and Anu to quantitatively analyze
the variability we're seeing in these Forks
um so what I'm showing here uh is the result of
that principal comparing analysis initially for
the CM contracts and another group of extensively
equal to the contracts called the CI contracts and
these data from uh this compilation of study
that we published last year in epsl what you
can see is that the CM contracts when you look
at their principal components they fall largely
on a mixing line here between a Fork diagram
that's got a very nice Vortex characteristic
shape up to a Fork diagram here is what a very
nice single domain shape so basically these CM
chondrites the magnetic carriers can be described
as mixtures of varying proportions of Vortex State
magnetite and single domain magnetite this group
of meteorites here the CI conjugates they have a
different type of forward diagram and this is
this more triangular shape they are the greens
are interacting with each other spreading the
Fork diagram vertically and what we can see is
that these are not uh a natural end member of this
trend it's not like if you continue this trend you
would get to this point here so magnetics forming
in a different way in these meticulates to these
meteorites really interestingly when we add winch
coming to this it falls in between the two and we
can say that the two pieces of which can can
be described as a mixture of going somewhere
along this line about here and then mixing up by
adding in some of this material here so the rich
Community right appears to be enormously rich in
this end member of material given it is certainly
a CM chondray now this material here when we
look at under the microscope is framboids and
plaquettes and magnetite what happened here is we
originally had an iron sulfide that sulfide has
been aqueously altered and it dissolved and then
in the void space magnetite is reprecipitated as
these tight clusters and magnetite grains and then
it doesn't show up super clearly in these pictures
here but these briquettes are stacked platelets
of magnetite which form through a similar process
in the normal CM chondrites the main form of
magnetite was simply that we had eye nickel
metal water comes in and pseudomorphically
replaces the metal grain with magnetite so
in Winchester we've got two forms of magnetite
forming one through dissolution and precipitation
and one through pseudomorphic replacement which
is anomalous most CM contracts don't show this
um so this means given that these magnetic phases
form direct result duration and these meteorites
did not experience high peak temperatures
we expect the recorded chemical remnant
magnetizations of the disk field or crms and this
is the case for any low temperature contrary the
cim chondrites cochondrates CV chondrites and
any ungrouped low temperature contracts as well
now just probably show the data from whichcom I'm
going to quickly show uh what most CM contracts
look like in their demagnetization patterns so
I'm showing an orthogonal projection plot over
here from a paper from a few years ago now
and we can see that by 100 ml Tesla there is
a broadly origin trending component but it's
by no means that the origin is not completely
demagnetized and we see that most of the nrm
when you heat it is lost by about 300 degrees C
and these two results combined suggest that it's
a resonance predominantly carried by a pyrotite
um which is kind of interesting because there's
certainly magnetite in this meteority if you see
on the microscope we see it in xid and
we also see it in the magnetism as well
there is a signal that demagnetizes above the
periotic hearing temperature all the way up to
the magnetic area temperature so it seems like
only the period is magnetized in this meteorite
and this corresponds to um a paleontensity of four
plus or minus three micro tester so significantly
weaker than Earth's field today corresponding
to that value I showed on that compilation a few
slides ago now winchcomb shows something quite
different what I'm showing here the orthogonal
projection plots from three samples of winchcomb
bulk samples measured in our 2G downstairs in our
paleo Mac lab here and we're seeing large local
security components medium coated components and
then origin trending higher activity components
the low capacity components are not unidirectional
from sample to sample whereas the high quality
of your components start to become much closer
to unidirectional from sample to sample and
we're also seeing them carried up to at least 85
millitester so relatively High coercivity carriers
we didn't perform any thermal measurements because
these meteorites in my experience at least alter
very very easily on heating so we thought given
this was a precious sample we would AF all of
our samples rather than the Chinese thermal
magnetization but winchcomb appears to carry a
large origin trending Hydro shifting component
but not too as high but it's going to relatively
High AF values but not as high as most normal CM
contributes looking at equal area plot projections
of the different components we can see that the we
have three different types of songs we measured
one is the fusion crust which is the part of the
meteorite that gets really hot when it enters the
atmosphere and creates the firewall itself this
melts so we know this re-records Earth's field we
then have a bait Zone where we have material from
right next to the fusion crust and it got warm
on Earth but didn't melt and then the interior
which doesn't appear heated at all in the low
coaster component diffusion crusted material
of course Earth field is pointing in a different
direction to any of the Interior or big samples
and the medium coercivity the fusion crust is
in a different direction to the low coercivity
and then the other samples seem to fall on an
arc extending away from that to a direction
that sort of south south east and then in high
coercivity we're seeing unidirectionality among
diffusion crusted samples the bake samples and the
interior circles from closest to the fusion crust
but then a completely different direction
which corresponds to an end member on this
block for the higher cohesivity Direction
suggesting that there is a pre-terrestrial
primary remnants carried in uh the the most
interior subsamples inside which although it was
particularly affected by atmospheric entry we were
able to see through that in most of our subsamples
the location component is almost
certainly a terrestrial brm
the MC component appears to be a mixture between
that terrestrial overprint and the high quality
component and a high quality component
appears to be a primary terrestrial signal
we did uh arm uh paleo intensity determination
among all of our sub samples uh and we're seeing
stronger values than what we saw in the normal
CM contracts as well sort of uh somewhere between
about 10 and 20 microtesla for our samples uh
here's a compilation of all of the samples that
showed relatively high quality demagnetization
and we get an average value of 15 and a half micro
Tesla now if this parent asteroid was recording
its magnetization during aqueous alteration and
the disk field was a constant orientation and
this body was spinning that means we record on
average depending on the Tilt to the spin axis
half are paying attention that's half the value
of the background field so to correct for that
we have to double the value we recover so we
proposed at the nebula field recorded by the
winter committee rate was 31 micro Tesla and
according to some work that Leslie did a few
years ago now the magnetic range inside these
Fanboys the predominant magnetic carrier and
these meteorites have relaxation times of
millions of billions of years so we believe that
because it doesn't appear to be an overprint on
Earth that this should be a primary signature that
reflects the magnetic field recorded by uh which
came during the very early solar system during
equatorial duration within this magnetite formed
now we can add that to that compilation I
showed earlier and if anything rather than
making things more straightforward I've I've
I've complicated things more I expected it to
fall on top of the music rates that come from
the same group and it's an order of magnitude
stronger which was not what I was hoping for
I was hoping for a relatively straightforward
story to talk about a fresh meteorite and uh
we've got something that we weren't expecting
um so given we have this new observation we
we proposed a theory as to why that might
be and it's sort of really Illuminating to
think about the magnetic carriers we have in
each of these meteorites so just adding those
on in the refrigerator it's recorded stronger
intensities they all have primary eye nickel
metal as a magnetic recorder Winchester that's
got ramboidal magnetite that magnetite that
forms this geomorphic replacement and purity
the CM contracts the normal ones have magnetite
that forms between water replacement and periotite
and then these two just have magnetite so it's
interesting that there seems to be a correlation
between what the magnetic primary magnetic carrier
is and the pale intensity it records so that led
us to propose a model let's imagine that we've
got our pre-alteration magnetic assemblage which
in the in a CM contract a typical one would be
grains of metal that are non-unidirectionally
magnetized alongside stoichiometric iron sulfide
Twilight which is also non-magnetic which is
non-magnetic and which can look similar a normal
CM contract then undergoes aqueous alteration
uh the metal reacts with water to create
magnetite and the Twilight reacts with water to
create Purity now it's possible that the magnetite
inherits the remnants from its parent metal that's
been observed in other crms recording terrestrial
Cycles before that can't be the case for pyrotype
because the parent phase is non-magnetic so it's
possible that if there is a weak background field
shown here by the gray arrows that the magnetite
doesn't care it doesn't see that because it's
inheriting the remnants from its metal whereas
the piritay does because the parent's non-magnetic
in winchcomb we had the same thing happening
with the metal but when the thromboidal magnetite
forms uh in when it replaces the Twilight that
forms through dissolution and reprecipitation so
that can't inherit any parent Metals it's not
forming through trigonometric replacement now
it's forming through a new magnetite grain
that forms through precipitation so that's
much more likely to correspond to a classical
CRM where we would record the background field
now the problem we have in all of these meteorites
is when we go into the lab and we magnetize them
to get our calibration arm measurement we
magnetize everything because we have to we
have to apply magnetic field to the whole sample
which magnetizes all the magnetite and all the
periotite and this means that when we do our arm
period intensity determination in a typical CM
contract we're demagnetizing when we demagnetize
the arm both perotite and magnetite whereas can
be demand as the nrm we're only demagnetizing
piritate which is a small magnetic it's called
a low susceptibility and has a low magnetization
so the change we see in our y-axis measurement
is going to be way less than what we see in our
x-axis measurement and that's going to shallow our
slope and give us a weak paleo intensity far lower
than what could have actually been the background
field at the time and the same stream winchcombe
but to less of an extent here the puritate and
the thromboider magnetite are magnetized but we're
still magnetizing the pseudomorphic magnetite when
we do our lab calibration which gives us a steeper
slope but still doesn't match that one to one we'd
expect if we'd applied the rate the natural
field strength when we did our arm calibration
so what I did was some back of the envelope
calculations to basically say is the amount
of thromboid magnetite we have in which can
consistent with the pain intensity we measure
and we can get out a quantitative measure of
the flamboyant the proportion family that we
have from those four diagrams I showed earlier
and what we can basically say is if we have
um an original field that was 77 micro Tesla
if we record about half of that because about
half magnetized framboid magnetite that would
give us this 31 micro tester value we measure
so we have this back in the calculation based
on susceptibility uh that says the bank field
should do this as a function of how much from
bio-duplicate magnetics in there and for the value
we measure independently for four diagrams that
overlaps what we measure in our pale intensity
uh if we then take that 77 micro tester value
and we can calculate the field we would measure
in a normal CM contract one that has only
pseudomorphic replacement magnetite and peritone
that would give us um this sort of Contour
diagram here where I'm showing the proportion
of magnetite possible in the proportion of
type possible highlighting in the lighter
colors the more likely values we get from
xrd measurements of these meteoroids we
can see that we are for a nominal two and
a half percent of protect magnetite we are
recreating the four micro tester value almost
perfectly that we measure in these meteorites
so it looks like no CM contract is actually able
to record the intensity of its background field
because only a portion of its magnetic minerals
are able to record a magnetization but when we
account for that proportion all CM contracts
are consistent with a 77 microtesla value if
now meteorites that have neither perotite nor
thromboid magnetite would look like they weren't
magnetized in this scenario even if there was a
field and that becomes important oh sorry I should
say I've proposed this theory that does Fanboys
implicate magnetite have a different element if
you just pseudomorphic magnetite and if so why
and I haven't been able to support that with a
concrete observation because it doesn't exist yet
but we have our new Quantum Diamond microscope
our geoqdm operating fully in Oxford now it's
running as I speak looking into this problem
so hopefully in a few months time I'll be able to
give you concrete observations that support this
now when we account for the intensity that we
measure in these meteorites and their proportion
of thrombroid magnetite or puritate we can say all
the CM contracts actually correct this value of 77
and then these two meteorites which don't have
irritate and don't have any thrombroid magnetite
just weren't able to record a magnetic field so we
can drop them from our record and we immediately
get a much more straightforward record where
we're just seeing a strong magnetic field as a
function of time among the carbonation contracts
of around 80 to 100 microtesla or so so although
winch can initially seemed to be a complicated
meteority didn't agree with anything else using
its anomalous mineralogy we've kind of actually
been able to produce a new model that appears to
clarify quite a few issues in the magnitude field
in the carbon issues quadrate to formation region
solar system appears strong now uh we've been over
the last sort of 10 years doing a lot of isotopic
measurements and meteorites and when we look
at their nuclear synthetics we can see that all
meteorites fall into two families the carbonaceous
contracts up here which I've been talking about
today and the non-carbonationists down here
and this difference in isotopic compositions
strongly supports a bifurcation of our disc our
productivity disc was separated into two somehow
and they had two isotopically distinct evolving
reservoirs and we think that this Reservoir the
carbonaceous uh originates from further away from
the Sun and this Reservoir the non-carbonate just
from closer to the Sun and what I'm just going
to show you to finish up the talk is uh the pain
intensity recover from a non-carbonation meteorite
that formed motor to the Sun and our new sort of
19 micro tester value that the carbonation
chondrites are pointing towards and what we
can immediately see this is this prediction I
showed for the magnetic field intensity on a
previous slide is that the combination don't agree
with this prediction they are twice as strong as
a non-carbonaceous meteorites about three times
as strong as they're predicted nominal magnetic
field intensity and there are several ways of
explaining this but one of them could be if we did
indeed have a pressure Maxima that meant that our
disc's magnetic field looked something like this
if we had a pressure Maxima that would concentrate
magnetic field lines and potentially explaining
this fact of two difference we're seeing in the
magnetic field intensity so just to conclude the
original carries a unidirectional High character
that appears to be a primary signature from
the early solar system this corresponds to a
comparatively strong magnetic field of 31 micro
Tesla which is about an automatically stronger
than we see recorded from other cm quadrates and
we can start to propose a way of explaining this
difference um by anything about the mineralogy and
it suggests that the intensity of the magnetic
field was strong in the carbonaceous reservoir
in our solar system and when we combine that
with all the other meteorites that we've got
so far they're all consistently pointing towards
this idea that the carbonation metric recorded a
particularly strong magnetic field which could
most readily be explained by a heterogeneity
or some sort of pressure Maxima inside of
our protection disc which could shed some
really valuable light on environments that led to
Planet formation thank you everyone for listening
thank you very much thanks
uh there are many applauses for you
thank you very much very interesting talk
um there is now room for some questions I
see win raise his hand just please go ahead
hi James well what a fantastic talk oh gosh I
don't know I mean I've got loads of things that
come to my mind so uh just on a technical thing
I'm always slightly suspicious about PCM modeling
because it depends upon your end States right yeah
and I I personally I'm not convinced uh about but
I don't think it really it doesn't actually odd to
any of your conclusions but the the identification
of a Vortex stayed from Vortex from four times
I think is pretty dubious uh if you have some uh
single amazes and interactions then I think
you can get a very similar characteristic
um but uh so the rest of the questions I have
I read because my lack of knowledge I mean I so
um the uh the you think that the uh carpenticious
chondrites always form further out in the
protoplasmic disc was that what you said yeah and
I should have I it slipped my mind to say exactly
why we think that they have a higher amount of
uh phylosilicates and secondary phases at the
present day which means we think they had more
solid ice Incorporated when they're accreted and
solid ice is stable further away the disk where
it's cooler so it's something with the amount of
um water we think is in the meteorites and
how the function I guess varies as a function
of temperature stability and the reason why
the uh sort of field or the the protoplasmic
magnetic field is it varies with the density of um
nebula material is because of some ionization or
something it's to do with both an ish impactor
and also the um the magnetic field sort of has
a you can think about a magnetic pressure that
it exerts a force and there's also a force from
the the temperature uh in the disk as well and
those two balance each other and they they all
depend on on the pressure I guess you could
think about it as if you had something like
um like a like a solenoid if you have a material
that can attract magnetic flux lines they will go
into that so you can just have more Jets material
it amplifies the field okay well right for some
reason I never knew that so that's amazing so
the last thing I have just a question is um this
uh which is critical to your interpretation is the
uh the origin of the remnants and whether material
can inherit the original magnetization so that and
that's that's what I would when when you emailed
me earlier that's the question I want to propose
to the to the community I have invoked this
um based on my observation and it appears to
correlate but I don't have the evidence to
support it right now as I said we've got our qdm
and we're measuring clusters of magnetite that
form to pseudomorphic replacement and framboiding
magnetite and seeing if they're if all of the uh
pseudomorphic magnetite is no New Direction with
all the thrombroid is unidirectional that would
be a nice bit of smoking that evidence we've got
another set of um experiments planned but what I'd
love to see is anyone who's got some sort of um
uh any way of modeling this having a metal grain
looking at magnetization and changing that into
magnetite and seeing what can be inherited through
that transition well that'd be really cool and I
think that's something that we're definitely able
to do and Jose who is uh a student of uh Tom Burns
who's who's here at the moment you can see uh he's
doing that that exactly that for the planet yes
but actually the um there's something definitely
we could do for the flamboiders that'd be really
interesting to see uh if that is able to inherit
um and you said that and of course the peritone
doesn't but um yeah so that that was that was
really cool I mean just an amazing uh set of set
of data and a story that you've built around it
just amazing like I I don't think I'm ever
going to be as fortuitous in my career again
and it's having a meteorite land uh basically
on my doorstep that really helps clarify this
complicated picture that we've been building
in the last seven or eight years that's it's
just not gonna happen again I I feel very I
feel very privileged yeah but fantastic work
James really impressed thanks thank you thank
you thank you um Greg you have your hand up
yeah it's been said that was a really good talk
I mean I guess actually um my question kind of
follows on a little bit from from what when
was talking about I mean um how exactly are
you calibrating your period of intensity so you're
using an ERM uh based method which are almost all
calibrated assuming that the nrm is a thermal
magnetization but but you don't have that you
have a CRM so how are you doing the calibration
and how might that actually impact um um your your
potential estimate you're absolutely right so we
are uh again basically due to a lack of of really
concrete observations we're assuming that the CRM
is the same as a trm and there are you know Buffy
McClellan did some very premium measurements back
in the 90s that suggests the long time periods
that ratio of um CRM to trm is is closer to one
but we don't have the measurements to to back that
up again we're starting a set of projects uh in a
few months are going to be doing that explicitly
for lab altered meteorites take anhydrous
meteorites put them in water then measure them
magnetization so we'll get an idea we'll get a
calibration but in the time being we're using that
value of one for the arm to trm ratio we're using
a factor of 3.3 which is the average that people
have measured from calibration studies in the past
so you're absolutely right we don't we don't have
um as much data yet to to give the really concrete
values we want I guess uh a really interesting
thing is um regardless of the calibration factors
the CM contracts can be compared to each other in
relative sense and we're still seeing an
order magnitude more in this meteorating
um and um that order magnitude is
consistent with the proportion of
franwood magnetite we're seeing in in this
meteor so I think even if the numbers end
up moving around that relativity the fact
that this is an automation stronger will
still stand and that's one of the
key the key observations I I think
it'd be cool to to look at that CRM trm ratio
from a modeling perspective as well
absolutely absolutely yeah definitely
thank you uh for your question thanks um is
there any other question from the audience
right so um let's give James another big round
of applause thanks for presenting to Madness
thank you everyone
um I'm gonna share last few slides with you
so um I would like to remind you that
our next talk is going to be in the
19th of October from just learner and then
in November we have two dates uh Joe Merck
and then keep it uh we keep you updated on
the main list so please subscribe to that
if you haven't and if you have missed the
past seminar or you want to catch up with
is Washington reward you please follow us
like the YouTube page you can cite also the
the talks through a GUI and and so thanks
again for joining us and see you next time